Okay, today's דף daf is דף נ"ג, daf nun gimmel, 53. We
pick up at the very last line of נ"ב עמוד ב', nun
bais amud bais, נפל לפניו. nafal lifanav. And our learning should be
in the זכות zechus of all of the חיילים וחיילות chayalim v'chayalos
and all the innocents that are in harm's way, and we should
just have a speedy end to the war and safety and security
return to the land and the return of all of the hostages.
All right, now נפל לפניו. nafal lifanav. So the משנה mishna said
that if somebody is digging in the pit and it startled the
animal and the animal fell forward, נפל לפניו, nafal lifanav, into the
pit, then the owner of the pit is liable, and if it
fell backwards, the owner of the pit is exempt. So what exactly
does this mean, fell backwards? We know what fell forward into the
pit means. What does falling backwards mean? So let's take a look.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, says Rav, לפניו לפניו ממש לאחריו לאחריו ממש
וזה וזה בבור. lifanav lifanav mamash, l'acharav l'acharav mamash, v'zeh v'zeh b'bor.
So Rav says it means literally fell face first into the pit
or fell backwards into the pit. Its mouth and its face facing
upwards and it's falling into the pit. Or falling into the pit,
we wouldn't have a discussion whether the owner of the pit is
liable or not. So then why is the owner exempt if the
ox was facing backwards and got startled and fell into the pit?
That would certainly seem to be a perfect example of the pit
causing the damage. So the גמרא Gemara says, רב לטעמיה, Rav l'taimei,
Rav is going according to his reasoning, the discussion we had a
few days ago, דאמר רב, d'amar Rav, בור שחייבה עליו תורה, bor
shechiyva alav torah, להבלו ולא לחבטו. l'havalo v'lo l'chavato. The pit that
the תורה Torah obligates you for is because of the הבל, hevel,
the air in the pit, and not because of the impact with
the ground. So obviously that's very difficult to
understand, as was discussed in the earlier גמרא. Gemara. Obviously it is
the impact of the ground that breaks its bones and so on,
but presumably this is reflecting the idea that, well, the ground is
קרקע עולם. karka olam. I didn't create the ground, so I'm not
responsible for that. I only created the cavity,
the well, what's not ground. So you could sort of say I
created the air there and the air quality and so that's mine.
The ground was always the ground.
So and
therefore you need to be able to make a claim that the
הבל hevel did something. And therefore if the animal is falling face
up, the sense is that it is breathing the air outside of
the well and it is not the הבל hevel that's impacting the
animal. It's an interesting claim. You could say even if it's face
up, it's getting some of the הבל hevel in the well. But
that's how he explains the משנה. mishna. Okay, and therefore if it
falls backwards, you're exempt. ושמואל אמר, v'Shmuel amar, and Shmuel says, בבור
בין מלפניו בין מלאחריו חייב. b'bor bein milifanav bein mil'acharav chayav. If
it fell into the well, it doesn't matter face first or backwards,
you're going to be חייב. chayav. שמואל לטעמיה דאמר להבלו וכל שכן
לחבטו. Shmuel l'taimei d'amar l'havalo v'chol shekein l'chavato.
Shmuel says, yes, the תורה Torah obligated you for creating the הבל
hevel of the בור, bor, but it certainly if somehow there was
a case that it was filled with pillows and it died only
because of asphyxiation, you'd be חייב, chayav, but it certainly has obligated
you for the impact against the
ground. You are considered to have created that. The ground was there
always, but it wasn't a hole before. So the opportunity for it
to impact the ground and it's your well which includes the walls
of the pit. So therefore even if it falls backwards and there's
no הבל hevel that injured it, you're still going to be חייב.
chayav. Okay, so then how do you explain the משנה? mishna? אלא
היכי דמי לאחריו דכל קריאה דפטור? ella heichi dami l'acharav dechal k'reia
depatur? What's the case of the משנה mishna when it falls backwards
due to the sound of digging that the owner of the pit
is exempt? כגון שנתקל בבור ונפל לאחורי הבור חוץ לבור. kigon shenitkal
b'bor v'nafal l'achorei habor chutz labor. It tripped over the well, the
edge, it made it stumble, but then it actually fell outside of
the well. So לפניו lifanav means it fell into the well and
לאחריו l'acharav it means it fell outside of the well, behind the
well, not into the well.
And therefore it is going to be exempt. You might say, why
should it be exempt? I mean the בור bor was a hazard
and even though it hit the ground outside of the בור, bor,
let it be like the גמרא Gemara's case of אבנו סכינו ומשאו.
avnos sakino umaso. You put a stone in the middle of רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, somebody trips over it and hits their face on
the ground, that's okay, you're going to be חייב, chayav, especially שמואל
Shmuel that doesn't need הבל. hevel. So the answer is that if
the animal had just tripped on the edge and fell outside, yes,
you would be חייב. chayav. That would be a בור bor like
אבנו סכינו ומשאו. avnos sakino umaso. It was the hazard even though
the ground was the ground of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. But here
the tripping was caused because of the guy digging in the well.
So therefore the guy digging in the well is what startled it.
He is considered to have— the one to do the tripping, and
therefore, unless you can have the owner of the בור Bor to
be the one who did the damage, the owner of the בור
Bor will be exempt. Okay, so again, according to רב, Rav, the
owner of the בור Bor is exempt if he falls face up
because you need the הבל hevel to contribute to the injury that
was being done. And according to שמואל, Shmuel, the impact of the
בור Bor is always going to be obligate the person. So it
doesn't matter if face down, face up, always obligate. But if he
tripped on the בור Bor and fell outside of it, in that
case the cause the tripping was seen to be caused by the
digger, the person who made the בור Bor is fully exempt. Okay,
so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
איתיביה, Eisivei, I'll ask you on this.
בבור, Bebor, we have a ברייתא Baraisa that says if it fell
into the pit, בין מלפניו בין מלאחריו חייב, bein milfanav bein milachrav
chayav, whether face first or whether backwards, you're going to be obligated.
That's explicitly against רב. Rav. תיובתא דרב, Tiyuvta deRav, it's a contradiction
to רב. Rav. אמר רב חסדא מודה רב בבור ברשותו דחייב. Amar
Rav Chisda modeh Rav bebor bireshuso dechayav.
No, the case of that ברייתא Baraisa is talking about it was
a well in your property that you dug in your property. You
know, the גמרא Gemara sort of speaks about you were מפקיר mafkir
the property around it, so the person, you know, had a right
to be using it, but you actually owned the בור Bor itself.
And in that case, it's not קרקע עולם. karka olam. In that
case, you are חייב chayav for the actual impact.
Alright? מודה רב בבור ברשותו, Modeh Rav bebor bireshuso, if you own
the בור Bor and again, the person has the right to be
traveling in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, but your בור Bor that
you own is right there in the
middle, so דחייב. dechayav. In that case, you're חייב, chayav, משום דאמר
ליה ממה נפשך אי בהבלא מית הבלא דידך הוא. mishum de'amar lei
mima nafshach ei behavla mis havla didach hu. If it died because
of the הבל, hevel, the air in the בור, Bor, then you
created that air.
ואי בחבטא מית חבטא דידך הוא, Ve'ei bachavata mis chavata didach hu,
it's your impact. The only reason רב Rav exempted for the impact
was because it was the property of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. But
if it's your property, then you're going to be חייב. chayav. Okay,
so that was the case in the ברייתא, Baraisa, alright, special case
of a בור ברשותו. bor bireshuso. רבא אמר הכא במאי עסקינן במתהפך
דנפל על אפיה ונתהפך ונפל על גביה. Rava amar hacha bemai askinan
bemis-hapech denafal al apei ve-is-hapech venafal al gabei. Okay,
we're talking about a case where in the end it did fall
backwards, back first, the back hit the ground of the pit, but
it first fell face first and you know, it inhaled all of
that הבל hevel and then it flipped around and the back hit
the bottom of the pit. Alright, and that's the case. דנפל על
אפיה, denafal al apei, it fell on its face, ואיתהפך, ve'ishapech, and
then it flipped over, ונפל על גביה, venafal al gabei, and then
it actually hit the back of it hit the bottom of the
pit. דהבלא דאהני ביה אהני ביה, dehavla de-ahani bei ahani bei, that
the הבל hevel that got into its face at the initial fall,
that contributed and therefore you're going to be חייב chayav for everything.
Again, neither of this sounded all like the case of the ברייתא.
Baraisa. The ברייתא Baraisa seemed to be trying to tell you it
doesn't matter face first or not face first and we have now
explained it either it's a special case of you owning the pit
or it's it does matter face first or not face first but
it was a case of having turned over. רב יוסף אמר הכא
בניזקי בור בשור עסקינן. Rav Yosef amar hacha benizkei bor beshor askinan.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said you misunderstood this ברייתא. Baraisa. We're not
talking about the owner of the pit being liable for the damage
to the ox, we're talking about the owner of the ox being
liable for damage caused to the water at the bottom. It's not
just a pit, it's a well. Okay? הכא בניזקי בור בשור עסקינן.
Hacha benizkei bor beshor askinan. מאי
ניהו שהבאיש מימיו? Mai nihu she-hiv'ish meimav? The ox fell in and
spoiled the water.
דלא שנא לפניו ולא שנא לאחריו מחייב. delo shana lefanav velo shana
leachrav mechayav. So it doesn't matter whether it was face up or
face down.
Your ox walked into my property. Have to be that it walked
into my property, it's like a שן ורגל, shen varegel, so it
has to be רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. Your ox walked into my
property without permission, fell into my well, destroyed the water, you're going
to be חייב. chayav. Again, does not seem like that from the
ברייתא. Baraisa. Why would the ברייתא Baraisa have to say it doesn't
matter face first or not if that's the scenario? Like, that obviously
should not even be anything that I would think would be relevant
to the conversation. But okay, we have a ברייתא Baraisa that seems
to go against רב Rav and he has three ways of explaining
it.
דלא שנא לפניו ולא שנא לאחריו מחייב. delo shana lefanav velo shana
leachrav mechayav. תני רבי חנינא לסיועיה לרב. Tani Rabbi Chanina lesiyu'ei leRav.
Now we're going to try to support רב. Rav. So רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina taught to support רב. Rav.
ונפל עד שיפול דרך נפילה. venafal ad sheyipol derech nefilah. It's a
דרשה, drasha, apparently a תנאית Tannaitic source, a דרשה drasha on the
פסוק pasuk ונפל שמה שור או חמור, venafal shama shor o chamor,
an ox or a donkey falls into it. And the דרשה drasha
is עד שיפול דרך נפילה. ad sheyipol derech nefilah. It has to
fall like things naturally fall, fall face first. Okay. אמרו, Amru, and
based on this they said, נפל לפניו מקול הכרייה חייב לאחריו מקול
הכרייה פטור, nafal lefanav mikol hakriyah chayav leachrav mikol hakriyah patur, that
if it fell face first because of the sound of the digging
you're obligated and if it fell backwards you are exempt. So because
it says you know it has to fall the normal way of
falling, it sounds like we're talking okay וזה וזה. veze veze. And
then it says explicitly, spells it out, וזה וזה בבור, Vezeh vezeh
babor, and the ברייתא Braita explicitly says and we're talking about that
it fell into the well. And nevertheless you're going to be exempt
if it didn't fall the natural way and if it fell backwards.
Okay, so that's the debate. אמר מר. Amar Mar. Now we're going
to look
at now we have one of two ways of explaining the משנה,
Mishna, but now we're going to look at the whole issue about
the fact that it is the digger that caused the animal to
stumble and how is that relevant and how should that be relevant
should that maybe get the owner of the well
off the hook. אמר מר, Amar Mar, נפל לפניו מקול הכרייה חייב.
Nafal lefanav mikol hakriya chayav. If the animal fell forwards everybody agrees
they're חייב, chayav, right, into the well. So the digger startled the
animal but at the end of the day the digger was the
hazard but at the end of the day the well was the
thing that did the damage. ואמאי, Ve'amai, says the גמרא Gemara but
why is that? נימא קול גרם ליה. Nema kol garam leh. Why
can't the owner of the well say of the בור bor say
the digger was the one that caused it to stumble? And this
points to the fact that a בור bor has two factors to
it. It both is a stumbling block, לפני עיוור לא תיתן מכשול,
Lifnei iver lo titein michshol, putting the stone in the רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim, it's a stumbling block, it causes the tripping to happen
and then it actually is the thing that does the damage, has
the impact, creating the damage. What happens if you separate it? So
in this case the digger caused the stumble and the well caused
the damage. Does the well, the בור, bor, the pit have to
actually cause the stumble in order for the owner to be liable?
So let's take a look.
ואמאי נימא קול גרם ליה. Ve'amai nema kol garam leh. Say it
was the digger that caused the stumble and that should get me
off the hook. אמר רב שימי בר אשי, Amar Rav Shimi bar
Ashi, הא מני רבי נתן היא. Ha meni Rabbi Natan hi. This
is רבי נתן Rabbi Natan דאמר, de'amar, who says,
דאמר בעל הבור היזיקא עביד. de'amar ba'al habor hazeika avid. First point
of רבי נתן Rabbi Natan is the בעל, ba'al, the owner of
the well of or of the pit does the damage, meaning even
if it didn't cause the stumble since it actually did the impact
and did the act of damage that's enough to be liable even
if something else caused the stumble. Plus, וכל היכא דלא אפשר לאישתלומי
מהאי משתלם מהאי, Vechol heicha delo efshar leishtalumi mehai mishtalem mehai, and
if you can't collect from the guy who made it fall, who
caused the stumble, then you can collect full from the owner of
the pit. So number one the owner of the pit does not
need to cause the stumble to be liable and number two if
the person who caused the stumble can't be made to collect you
can collect fully from the owner of the pit. Because maybe you
should have said they should have split it and maybe the guy
who was doing the digging should have to pay half because he
also caused the stumble and since you can't collect because that was
only a גרמא, grama, it's not like he put a rock in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, causing the animal startling the animal through the
sound of your digging is a גרמא grama and you're exempt, so
maybe you should only be able to collect half from the owner
of the pit. No, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says two things. Number
one is it's enough that the pit did the damage and if
you can't divide the payment between the owner of the pit and
the one who caused the stumble because here that person is a
גרמא, grama, you can make your full collection from the owner of
the pit.
Okay, משתלם מהאי. mishtalem mehai. דתניא, Detanya, now we're going to see
where this רבי נתן Rabbi Natan comes from.
שור שדחף את חבירו לבור. Shor shedachaf et chaveiro labor. An ox
pushed a fellow ox into the into the pit. בעל השור חייב
בעל הבור פטור. Ba'al hashor chayav ba'al habor patur. So the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says it's all the owner of the ox. The
owner or the owner of the ox has to pay full, that's
a case of קרן, keren, let's say it was intentionally כוונה להזיק,
kavana lehazik, has to pay and not the owner of the well.
So why the owner of the ox has to pay, fine, it's
קרן. keren. Why not the owner of the well or of the
pit, of the בור? bor? Because presumably for the rabbis if the
בור bor does not create the stumble then you're exempt. The בור
bor has to actually do the act of stumbling. So in the
case of our משנה, Mishna, if the sound of the digging caused
the ox to fall face forward into the pit, according to the
חכמים, Chachamim, the owner of the pit would be fully exempt because
here he didn't cause the his pit didn't cause the stumble and
the guy who was doing the digging would be exempt because that
was a גרמא, grama, so you would be totally unable to collect.
That's what the rabbis say, you focus on the one that caused
the stumble. So in this case it would be the owner of
the ox if the ox did it you pay full, if the
digger did it it would be גרמא grama and there would be
no payment but it all goes to the one who caused the
stumble. That is the חכמים. Chachamim. רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Natan omer,
now רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says, בעל השור משלם מחצה ובעל הבור
משלם מחצה. Ba'al hashor meshalem mechtza uva'al habor meshalem mechtza. That they
split it. That you can be liable for your בור bor even
if it just did the damage and it didn't cause the stumble.
So but the owner of the ox is also that was... So,
but the owner of the ox is also, that was קרן. keren.
So, we're going to split it, each one pays half. Okay, so
if we just pause here, the debate is when the תורה Torah
made you liable for a בור, bor, is it, does the בור
bor have to create the stumbling for you to be liable or
is it enough that it creates the damage? The חכמים Chachamim say
it has to create the stumbling. So, if something else caused it,
an ox pushed it in, the sound of the jackhammer caused it
to be startled, then the owner of the בור bor is off
the hook and you have to try to collect from the one
that caused the stumbling. רבי נתן Rabbi Noson says they're both liable.
The בור bor is enough to create the damage, so they're both
liable. If it's an ox and a well, split it 50/50. If
it's a, if it's the jackhammer and the well, then the owner
of the well pays full. Okay. So now the גמרא, Gemara, now
we're going to clarify that second point: כל היכא דליכא לאשתלומי מהאי
משתלם מהאי, Kol heicha de-leika le-ishtalumey mei-hai mishtalum mei-hai, that if you
can't collect from the jackhammer guy, you can collect fully from the
owner of the בור. bor. Let's see how we know that. So
far רבי נתן Rabbi Noson has only said you split it.
So the גמרא Gemara says: והתניא רבי נתן אומר בעל הבור משלם
ג' חלקים ובעל השור רביע. Ve-hatanya Rabbi Noson omer ba'al ha-bor mishalem
gimmel chelaka'in ve-ba'al ha-shor revi'a. But wait a minute, we've got one
ברייתא braisa that רבי נתן Rabbi Noson says split 50/50. We have
another ברייתא braisa that רבי נתן Rabbi Noson says that the owner,
the ox owner, the owner of the ox pays a quarter and
the owner of the בור bor pays three-quarters.
How does that make sense? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא קשיא
הא בתם הא במועד. Lo kashya ha be-tam ha be-mu'ad. The difference
of תם tam and מועד mu'ad because we're dealing with קרן. keren.
So if it's a case of מועד, mu'ad, you know, the owner
of the ox has full liability, the owner of the well has
full liability, they split it 50/50. If it's תם tam and מועד,
mu'ad, let's take a look at how, if it's a תם tam
did the goring or the pushing, let's see how that plays out.
So the גמרא Gemara says: ובתם מאי קסבר? U-ve-tam mai kasavar? Now
let's see what he, רבי נתן, Rabbi Noson, holds in the case
of a תם. tam. אי קסבר האי כולי היזיקא עביד והאי כולי
היזיקא עביד, Ei kasavar hai kulei heizeika avid ve-hai kulei heizeika avid,
האי משלם פלגא והאי משלם פלגא. hai mishalem palga ve-hai mishalem palga.
So how do we conceptualize when they were partners in crime, when
it was the ox and the well that did it? We can
either say each one has 100% liability. So, you know, the owner
of the ox is liable full, the owner of the well is
liable full. Obviously, the guy's not going to get double for his
damaged, you know, cow, so they split the payment but fundamentally they
start with 100% liability. If that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, then
in a case of a תם, tam, the owner of the ox
has full liability, the full cost of, we'll call it a cow,
but because it's a תם, tam, pays half. Fine. 50% he pays,
50% and the owner of the well, of the בור, bor, pays
50%. How do you get down to a quarter if you start
conceptually with full liability?
So the
גמרא Gemara says: ואי קסבר האי פלגא היזיקא עביד והאי פלגא היזיקא
עביד, Ve-ei kasavar hai palga heizeika avid ve-hai palga heizeika avid, if
you start conceptually not like it's 100 and 100 but 50/50. So
if that's the case,
בעל הבור משלם פלגא, ba'al ha-bor mishalem palga, the owner of the
pit pays half because he did half the damage, ובעל השור רביע,
u-ba'al ha-shor revi'a, and the owner of the ox should pay a
quarter. He did half the damage and he's, it's a תם, tam,
so half of a half is a quarter. ואידך רביע מפסיד, ve-idach
revi'a mafsid, and the other quarter the owner of the cow would
be just lost. Okay, so if you really think each one did
50%, the גמרא's Gemara right, then it stands to reason that it's
50% and a quarter and a quarter doesn't get paid for because
that was what the ox did and the ox pays only half.
But if it's 100 and 100%, you can understand how in the
end the division is going to be three-quarters and a quarter, which
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, says רבא: Rava: רבי נתן דיינא הוא ונחית לעומקא דדינא. Rabbi
Noson dayana hu ve-nachit le-umka de-dina. רבי נתן Rabbi Noson was a
דיין dayan and he got to the very depth of the matter
of this law. לעולם קסבר האי כולי היזיקא עביד והאי כולי היזיקא
עביד. Le'olam kasavar hai kulei heizeika avid ve-hai kulei heizeika avid. He
held that each one is considered to have done 100%. ודקקשיא לך
לשלם האי פלגא והאי פלגא, Ve-de-ka-kashya lech le-shallem hai palga ve-hai palga,
and you said, oh but okay, so the owner of the ox
did 100% and he pays 50% of that because it's a תם,
tam, he pays 50%, and the owner of the, of the בור
bor pays his half and pays 50%. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, משום דאמר ליה בעל השור לבעל הבור, mishum de-amar lei ba'al
ha-shor le-ba'al ha-bor, because the, you know, the owner of the ox
says to the owner of the בור: bor: שותפותאי מאי אהני לי,
shutafutai mai ahanei li, that what good did this partnership do for
me? If my ox had done it all, I would pay 50%
because it's a תם. tam. Now that my ox did it all
and your well did it all, why should I still be paying
50%? You're also in the equation, so we should be splitting my
50%, all right, which actually, you know, makes sense, right? Because if
you think about it, you know, each one did 100%. So that
would mean that had they been alone, the owner of the well
would have paid $100, let's say the ox, the cow is worth
100, and had the owner of the ox and had the ox
done it alone, the owner of the ox would have paid $50.
Now they're both here into the פרשה parsha and you're not going
to pay, you know, Now the what do you call it, you're
not going to pay the owner of the cow a hundred and
fifty dollars, so how are you going to divide it up? Well,
this guy would have had a hundred liability on his own, this
guy would have had a fifty liability on his own. So, you
know, a hundred and fifty and you divide it whatever and seventy-five
and twenty-five, it makes sense why, you know, that the fifty gets
divided in half. That that's a fair allocation since this person would
have had a hundred liability by himself and this would have only
had fifty liability by himself. Okay, so that makes a lot of
sense. And now let's talk about that in terms of the case
about the jackhammer. Okay, if you think that everybody is חייב chayav
a hundred percent, so the owner of the well is a hundred
percent, the jackhammer's a hundred percent. Since the jackhammer guy can't be
paying it all, you go and you make your full collection from
the person, you know, from the owner of the well. All right,
each one has full liability and you collect from the party you're
able to collect from. And if you're able to collect from both
parties, then you do a fair allocation and that gets you to
your seventy-five and twenty-five.
Okay, איבעית אימא, Iba'isayma, now the גמרא Gemara has another answer which
is a little harder to understand. If you want, you can say
the following: ולא אם קסבר האי פלגא היזקא עביד והאי פלגא היזקא
עביד, V'lo im kasavar hai palga hizeika avid v'hai palga hizeika avid,
each one did half. ודקשיא לך משום בעל הבור משלם פלגא בעל
השור משלם רביע ואידך רביע נפשיה, V'dikashya lach mishum Ba'al haBor meshaleim
palga Ba'al haShor meshaleim revia v'idach revia nafshei,
and you said one minute, then if they each did half of
it, the owner of the בור bor should pay fifty dollars, the
owner of the ox he did fifty dollars of damage, he should
pay half, that's twenty-five dollars, and then the guy should be out
twenty-five. How does that get thrown on the owner of the בור?
bor? So
the גמרא Gemara says: משום דאמר ליה בעל השור לבעל הבור Mishum
d'amar lei Ba'al haShor l'Ba'al haBor because the owner of the
ox says to the owner of the pit,
I found my cow at the bottom of your pit. את קטלתי,
At katlatei,
you killed it. מאי דאית לך לשלומי מהאי דאית לי לשלומי מהך
משתלמנא, Mai d'is lach lishalumi meihai d'is li lishalumi meihach mishtalamna,
what I can collect from the other guy, from the owner of
the ox I'll collect, but מאי דליתא לשלומי מהאי משתלמנא ממך, mai
d'leisa lishalumi meihai mishtalamna mimach, but if anything I can't collect from
him,
I'm going to collect from you. So what does that mean? I
mean, what it really sounds like it means, and תוספות Tosafos basically
says this, is it really sounds like it means it doesn't mean
fifty percent and fifty percent. It sounds like it means the owner
of the pit did a hundred percent and the ox is seen
as doing fifty percent. Okay, since the damage, the cow's at the
bottom of the pit and the impact was done by the pit,
even though it was pushed in by the ox, all right, you
can there according to רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan you start with like
full liability in terms of the owner of the of the בור,
bor, but you can deduct the liability that you can collect from
the ox. So the ox did fifty percent, you know, and half
of that because it's a תם, tam, twenty-five, but the hundred percent
liability what you can't that twenty-whatever else you can't collect you're going
to collect from the owner of the well. And that's כל היכא
דליכא לשלומי מהאי משתלמא ממך. kol heicha d'leika lishalumi meihai mishtalama mimach.
So רבי נתן, Rabbi Nassan, so one more time. The רבנן Rabbanim
say that the owner of the well is off the hook when
he did not cause the stumbling. And therefore and therefore in the
jackhammer nobody pays. In the case of the ox, the ox pays
full. You could also see from them the opposite of what we
just said for רבי נתן, Rabbi Nassan, which is they might say,
you know, the ox used the pit to kill this cow. So
therefore it's all on the ox, it's all on the one who
causes the initial stumbling. Everything else that happens is a consequence of
that. רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan says no, you split it when it's
an ox and a well and you can conceptualize that, says the
גמרא, Gemara, either as each one has a hundred percent liability. So
if there's somebody you can't collect from like the jackhammer guy or
the תם, tam, you know, whatever you would go and collect from
the owner of the well. Or what it sounds like at the
end, the owner of the well has a hundred percent and the
ox or the jackhammer guy has whatever has fifty percent. But at
the end of the day, anything you can't collect from other parties,
you can collect from the owner of the בור. bor. Okay, so
that's how our משנה Mishnah makes sense that even though the jackhammer
guy is off the hook, you can collect from the owner of
the בור. bor. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, five lines
from the bottom. הניח אבן על פי הבור בא שור ונתקל בה
ונפל בבור. Hiniach even al pi haBor ba shor v'niska bo v'nafal
baboor. So if you went ahead and put a rock at the
edge of so instead of the jackhammer and instead of a cow,
right, we're now going to have a rock in front of the
בור bor that causes the animal to stumble and fall into the
בור. bor. And again a normal animal wouldn't have done it, a
פיקח pikei'ach would have seen it, but because of the rock that
was the cause of the animal falling into the בור. bor.
בא שור ונתקל בה ונפל בבור, Ba Shor v'niska bo v'nafal babor,
באנו למחלוקת רבי נתן ורבנן. banu l'machlokes Rabbi Nassan v'Rabbanim. That's the
debate of רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan and the רבנן. Rabbanim. The רבנן
Rabbanim would say the owner of the rock pays the full amount,
that was the stumbling. So that's a type of a בור bor
on its own part, אבנו סכינו ומשאו, avno sakino umaso, and רבי
נתן Rabbi Nassan would say that they split it between the
two. The גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, that's obvious. Isn't that just
like, isn't the rock just like the cow? The ox that pushes
the cow in?
No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'seima, I might have thought התם הוא דאמרי
ליה בעל הבור לבעל השור. hasam hu d'amarei ba'al ha'bor l'ba'al ha'shor.
Let's start it again. פשיטא, pshita, isn't this obvious? No, מהו דתימא,
mahu d'seima, התם הוא דאמר בעל הבור לבעל השור hasam hu d'amar
ba'al ha'bor l'ba'al ha'shor that in the case of the ox and
the בור, bor, the owner of that's where the owner of the
pit can say to the owner of the ox, אילב בירא דידי
תורא דידך הוי קטיל ליה, ilav bira didi tora didach hava katil
lei, even had it not been for my pit,
your ox would have killed, your ox was goring and pushing and
so on, so therefore that's why for the רבנן Rabanan you have
full liability and for רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan half liability because the
ox could have done it without the well.
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but in this case מצי אמר ליה בעל
האבן לבעל הבור, matzi amar lei ba'al ha'even l'ba'al ha'bor, we could
think that the owner of the stone could say to the owner
of the well, אילב בורא דידך אבנא דידי מאי הוי עבדא, ilav
bura didach avna didi mai havai avda, had it not been for
your well,
my stone wouldn't have done anything. אי הוי מתקיל בה, i havai
miskel bah, even if the animal had tripped on my stone, if
it had tripped and there was no בור, bor, הוי נפל וקאי,
havai nafal v'ka'i, it would have fallen and gotten back up. So
in this type of a case, I, the owner of the stone,
should be totally exempt. Okay? So, and
you should pay full for רבי נתן, Rabbi Nassan, and for the
רבנן Rabanan maybe we're both exempt. But my stone did nothing by
itself. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so it teaches us that
in this case, no, it does apply the same debate, דאמר ליה,
d'amar lei, because אילב אבן לא הוי נפל לבירא, ilav even lo
havai nafal l'bira, had it not been for the stone, it would
not have fallen into the well. So yes, we sort of both
needed to do it together,
but damage was only caused in the end because of your stone
as well. So for רבי נתן, Rabbi Nassan, that's why even in
this case they would split it, and for the רבנן, Rabanan, that's
why in this case actually it would seem that the owner of
the stone has full liability, that even though it actually damaged itself
in the well, it's no different than the case of the ox,
and even though nothing would have happened without the well, at the
end of the day, the stone caused the stumbling. Okay, so it
actually does make sense that we had to tell me that even
in this case we put half or a hundred percent of the
responsibility on the owner of the stone, even though the well was
much more central in this case for the damage to have occurred.
Okay. איתמר, itamar, it was
taught, top of נ"ג ע"ב. nun gimel amud beis. שור ושור פסולי
המוקדשין שנגחו. shor v'shor pesulei ha'mukdashin she'nagchu. If you have two oxen,
an ox and an ox
of something sanctified that became invalid. And if you take a look
in the parentheses, מאי ניהו שור בכור דלא פריק ליה. mai nihu
shor bechor d'lo parik lei. So there's this commentary which is clearly
a gloss and it was put in by, it was from רב
האי גאון Rav Hai Gaon in the הלכות גדולות. Halachos Gedolos. It
says what we mean here is a firstborn ox that was not
redeemed, that had a blemish and was not redeemed. Why is that?
Because the גמרא Gemara is going to make it clear that this
שור פסולי המוקדשין shor pesulei ha'mukdashin is exempt from payment. And if
it were a case of an animal that had been sanctified
and got a blemish and redeemed, which is what פסולי המוקדשין pesulei
ha'mukdashin normally means, well, then that animal is considered for most purposes
to be like חולין. chulin. There's some restrictions how you can use
it. And
there would be no exemption if it would go ahead and do
damage. And from the case that we're about to read, it's clear
that this שור פסולי המוקדשין shor pesulei ha'mukdashin is a case where
there is exemption and the owner of that ox does not have
to pay. So it would be a case of an animal that
had a blemish that was not redeemed. Okay.
And even if it was a בכור bechor and it didn't have
to be redeemed and it could be eaten outside of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash without being brought as a קרבן, korban,
nevertheless, the fact that it was not redeemed and it had sanctity
would be enough to be, it would not be שור רעהו, shor
rei'eihu, your friend's ox, and the owner would be exempt. All right.
So anyway, we have an ox and an ox of invalid sacrifices,
sanctified thing that had a blemish that the owner is exempt from
paying, the owner of that ox, and they jointly gored. So אביי
אמר משלם חצי נזק. Abaye amar meshalem chatzi nezek. You pay the
owner of the ox that has to pay, the normal ox, pays
half. רבינא אמר משלם רביע נזק, Ravina amar meshalem revia nezek, pays
a quarter.
So now, how do we explain it? So the גמרא Gemara has
a couple of ways to explain what this debate is about. Maybe
it's a debate, maybe it's based on the circumstances.
הא והא בתם. ha v'ha b'tam. So one way to explain it
is we're talking about a תם, tam, and we're debating the רבנן
Rabanan and רבי נתן. Rabbi Nassan. How does this play out? Okay,
because if it's a תם, tam, so the רבנן, Rabanan, the assumption
here would be each one, they never introduced this principle of a
hundred percent and a hundred percent, okay? So each we would presume
that we take an idea that each one did fifty percent. So
the owner of the normal ox pays half of his fifty percent,
a quarter, and the guy is out the rest. Whereas according to
רבי נתן... Rabbi Nassan... רבי נתן, Rabbi Nosson, each one is seen
as doing a hundred percent, and since you can't collect anything from
the owner of the ox of the sanctified ox, so you collect
the full amount or the fifty percent of the full amount because
it's a תם tam from the owner of the normal ox. Okay?
So for the rabbis it's fifty-fifty and for רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson
it's a hundred-hundred and that would mean in a תם tam in
one scenario you get fifty, in one scenario you get twenty-five. You
know according to רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson you get fifty and according
to the rabbis twenty-five. That's one explanation. איבעית אימא iba'it eima if
you want you could say כרבנן. ke-Rabbanan. Okay? They're both going like
the rabbis that it's fifty-fifty. הא בתם הא במועד ha be-tam ha
be-muad and it depends if you know when the אביי Abaye said
that the guy that the owner of the ox of the normal
ox pays fifty, that's because it was a מועד. muad. So therefore
yes it's a fifty-fifty division. The owner of the normal ox did
fifty percent of the damage. It's a מועד muad so you pay
fifty. And רבינא Ravina says it's like the rabbis so it's a
fifty-fifty division. The owner of the ox has to pay for his
half, but because it's a תם tam pays a quarter. Okay. איכא
דאמרי ika d'amri others say אביי אמר חצי נזק רבא אמר כולי
נזק. Abaye amar chatzi nezek, Rava amar kulli nezek. אביי Abaye says
half, but now רבא Rava rather than saying a quarter says full.
הא והא במועד הא כרבנן והא כרבי נתן. ha ve-ha be-muad ha
ke-Rabbanan ve-ha ke-Rabbi Nosson. So one explanation is we're dealing with a
מועד muad and it's debate of רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson and the
רבנן. Rabbanan. רבנן Rabbanan is you know fifty-fifty division, fifty percent each,
so it's a מועד muad so the owner of the normal ox
pays fifty, the other half you're out. רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson it's
a hundred-hundred. The owner of the so therefore since you can't collect
anything from the owner of the sanctified ox, you're left with the
owner of the normal ox is left holding the bag כל היכא
דליכא לאשתלום מהאי משתלם מהאי. kol heicha d'leika le-ishtalum mei-hai mishtalum mei-hai.
Each one did a hundred percent so the owner of the normal
ox pays a hundred. Okay. איבעית אימא iba'it eima if you want
you could say הא והא כרבי נתן. ha ve-ha ke-Rabbi Nosson. They're
both going like רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson a hundred-hundred. הא במועד הא
בתם ha be-muad ha be-tam and it depends of a מועד muad
or a תם. tam. If it's a מועד muad then because we
can't collect from the sanctified ox the owner of the normal ox
has a hundred percent liability pays full. And if it's a תם
tam the owner of the normal ox has a hundred percent liability
and pays half. Okay. אמר רבא Amar Rava that was very interesting
but again it emphasized that it's not just a בור bor idea
of רבי נתן. Rabbi Nosson. Part of the debate of the רבנן
Rabbanan and רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson was does the בור bor focus
on the hazard or the damage but the other part of this
issue is do you view it as a hundred-hundred or fifty-fifty.
אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא Rava שור ואדם שדחפו לבור. shor
ve-adam she-dachafu le-bor. Now we're going to have you know this sort
of similar to some of רבא's Rava other scenarios like this reminds
us of some of like רבא's Rava scenarios at the end of
the second פרק. perek. But okay let's take a look. So if
an ox שור ואדם שדחפו לבור shor ve-adam she-dachafu le-bor if an
ox and a person push some you know animal or a human
being we'll see into a well. And by the way תוספות Tosfos
says that the human is doing it שלא בכוונה shelo bekavana because
if the human is doing it בכוונה bekavana then you know that
sort of he's seen as sort of the dominant force and everything
is sort of sub like is being used by the human being.
But we're talking about a case let's say according to תוספות Tosfos
that the human did it שלא בכוונה shelo bekavana and they pushed
and they pushed something into a well. לעניין נזיקין כולן חייבים. le-inyan
nezikin kullan chayavim.
So if it was let's say an ox that got damaged or
you know a human being that got injury and paying for the
נזק nezek the injury part of what happened then they would all
three of them divide it because all three of them you know
are this is probably following רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson where you don't
need where because for the rabbis the well would be off the
hook the owner of the well because it didn't cause the hazard
but for רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson all three did it and therefore
it's divided amongst all three of them. And that's why תוספות Tosfos
says the human has to be שלא בכוונה. shelo bekavana. If it
was the human בכוונה bekavana he says what if I take your
טלית tallis and throw it into somebody's fire that person is חייב
chayav for אש? eish? I'm using his fire. So I would be
using this guy's well. So it has to be the human did
it שלא בכוונה. shelo bekavana. Fine. Anyway and this is רבי נתן
Rabbi Nosson so we divide it equally between the three of them
כולן חייבים. kullan chayavim. לעניין ארבעה דברים le-inyan arba devarim if it
was a human that fell into the well and he got and
we're talking about you know injured and we're talking about the other
payment צער ריפוי שבת בושת tza'ar rippui shevet boshet so in that
case ודמי ולדות ve-demei veladot or a woman who God forbid miscarried
and you know and if that's done by a human then you
pay for the you know you pay for the
a monetary amount is assigned for the for the fetus. So אדם
חייב ושור בור פטור. adam chayav ve-shor bor patur. That's only a
liability that the תורה Torah assigns the שבת ריפוי בושת shevet rippui
boshet or the דמי ולדות demei veladot is only assigns for when
a human causes damages. So since it's רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson and
each one did a hundred percent so since the ox and the
and the בור bor don't pay anything the human pays full.
Okay now לעניין כופר ושלושים של עבד le-inyan kofer ve-shloshim shel eved
let's say a person fell in and got killed or slave fell
in and got killed. Okay so שור חייב אדם ובור פטורים. shor
chayav adam ve-bor paturim. So the תורה... Torah... Torah only assigns כופר
*kofer* for an ox; it doesn't assign, or the שלושים *shloshim* of
an עבד *eved* for if an ox gores a slave, it never
assigns it for a human being who causes a death and never
assigns it for a well. So again, since they're all one hundred
percent, you collect full from the ox. לעניין כלים kelim. *Le'inyan kelim*,
let's say some vessels broke, ושור פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim. *v'shor psulei
hamukdashim* or it was an ox that was פסולי מוקדשים *psulei mukdashim*
which we'll talk about in a minute, let's first focus on the
vessels, אדם ושור חייבים ובור פטור *adam v'shor chayavim u'vor patur*. Okay,
so the human and the ox are liable, right, because if you
cause damage to a cow even if it's a sanctified cow whatever
well we'll see in a minute what cow we're talking about but
also especially if you cause damage to vessels. So if a human
causes damage or an ox, you pay. But there's an exemption that
you don't pay for vessels that break in the pit, only for
the animals, not for the vessels. Therefore the owner of the pit
is פטור *patur* and the ox and the human split it equally.
Now what is this שור פסולי המוקדשים *shor psulei hamukdashim* that the
owner that the בור bor *bor*, the owner of the בור *bor*
is exempt from? So let's take a look. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this, okay, מאי טעמא
*mai ta'ama*, why by the שור פסולי *shor psulei* I mean כלים
*kelim* the גמרא *Gemara* knows, but why is there an exemption of
the owner of the pit for this ox of a sanctified animal?
So אמר קרא *amar kra*, the verse says והמת יהיה לו *v'hameit
yihyeh lo* במי שהמת שלו *bimishehameit shelo* יצא זו שאינו המת שלו
*yatza zu she'eino hameit shelo* because it says by the pit, you
know, you pay for the damage and you know and and you
have to take you know and the dead body is yours. So
it means the question is who's yours, the owner of the pit
or the original owner? But says the גמרא *Gemara*, it indicates that
the dead body can be used. And if the animal was sanctified,
even if it was redeemed or there's a whole question תוספות *Tosafot*
and רש''י *Rashi* I'm not going to get into it actually they
say here we're talking that it might not have been redeemed, but
without getting into the details, okay, under some circumstances here a sanctified
animal cannot be you know
used once it's dead, it can't be redeemed, אין פודים את הקדשים
להאכילם לכלבים *ein podin et hakodshim le'ha'achilam laklavim*, you can't redeem something
sanctified once the animal is dead that now you're just going to
use it as like נבילה *neveilah* meat. Alright let's just assume that
without getting into the קדשים *kodshim* details of that. Okay, so that's
why there's an exemption from the well because it's a dead animal
and it's not המת שלו *hameit shelo*. There's no way you can
use a dead animal of פסולי המוקדשים *psulei hamukdashim*. So says the
גמרא *Gemara*, okay, למימר דפשיטא ליה לרבא *lemaima dipshita lei l'Rava*, that
means that it's obvious to רבא *Rava* that there's this exemption of
פסולי המוקדשים *psulei hamukdashim* by a בור *bor*? והמיבעי בעי ליה לרבא
*v'hamiba'i ba'i lei l'Rava*, רבא *Rava* asked this question. איבעיא לרבא *iba'i
Rava*, רבא *Rava* asked, שור פסולי המוקדשים שנפל לבור מהו *shor psulei
hamukdashim shenafal l'bor mahu*. If an animal of you know that was
sanctified that now has a blemish falls into a בור *bor*, what's
the הלכה *halakhah*? האי והמת יהיה לו *hai v'hameit yihyeh lo*, when
it says והמת יהיה לו *v'hameit yihyeh lo* in the תורה *Torah*
by the case of the בור *bor*, במי שהמת שלו יצא זה
שאין המת שלו *bimishehameit shelo yatza ze she'ein hameit shelo* is when
the dead body has some use as opposed to when it was
a sanctified animal the dead body has no use and therefore you're
exempt? או דילמא *odilma* or do we say והמת יהיה לו *v'hameit
yihyeh lo*, בעלים מטפלין בנבילה הוא דאתא *b'alim metaplin b'neveilah hu d'ata*,
it's coming to tell us that whole סוגיא *sugya* we had earlier
that it is the original owner that still owns the dead body
and that the owner of the בור *bor* just pays for the
difference? So how come now רבא'ס *Rava's* taking it for granted in
this nice little layout about the ox and the well and the
person that there is this exemption? So the גמרא *Gemara* says בתר
דבעי הדר פשטיה *batar d'ba'i hadar pashtei*. Yeah, he had that question
and then in the end he decided, you know what, that is
how he's coming out, that there is an exemption for פסולי המוקדשים
*psulei hamukdashim* when it falls into a בור *bor*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says if that's true, אלא בעלים מטפלין בנבילה מנא ליה *ela
b'alim metaplin b'neveilah minalei*? So then where do you get this idea
that it is the original owner who have to deal with the
carcass? נפקא ליה מוהמת יהיה לו דשור *nafkah lei mi'v'hameit yihyeh lo
d'shor*. אה *ah*, because it says והמת יהיה לו *v'hameit yihyeh lo*
in another place. It says it when an ox gores an ox.
So there also it says you get the dead body. So there
it's teaching you a principle of בעלים מטפלין בנבילה *b'alim metaplin b'neveilah*,
that the owner keeps the carcass and the person who did the
damage pays the difference. So now the גמרא *Gemara* asks the obvious
question. מאי חזית דוהמת יהיה לו דשור מפקת ליה לבעלים מטפלין בנבילה
ווהמת יהיה לו דבור מפקת ליה למי שהמת שלו *mai chazeit d'v'hameit
yihyeh lo d'shor mafkit lei l'b'alim metaplin b'neveilah v'v'hameit yihyeh lo d'bor
mafkit lei l'mishehameit shelo*? What makes you say that the והמת יהיה
לו *v'hameit yihyeh lo*, the exact same words, by the ox tells
you this principle about the owner keeps the carcass and by the
well tells you a principle that there's a total exemption in the
case of a בור *bor* by פסולי המוקדשים *psulei hamukdashim*? איפכא נמי
*iphacha nami*, maybe I can reverse it? גמרא *Gemara* says no, מסתברא
פטור גבי בור הואיל ופטר בו את הכלים *mistabra p'tor gabei bor,
ho'il u'patar bo et hakelim*. You know, one of them has to
mean this exemption of פסולי המוקדשים *psulei hamukdashim* and it makes sense
to assign that to the case of the בור *bor* because the
בור *bor* has other things you're exempt from, you're exempt from כלים
*kelim*, you're exempt from if a person dies,
you know, you could also be so you're also going to be
exempt from פסולי המוקדשים *psulei hamukdashim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אדרבה
פטור גבי שור שכן פטר בו חצי *adderaba p'tor gabei shor shekein
patar bo chatzi* No, let's exempt the ox because an ox only
pays half damages. So that's leniency, so let's apply this leniency. So
the גמרא says no,
כולי נזק מי לא אשכחן. kulei nezek mi lo ashkan. We've never
found when an ox gores that it totally is exempt by a
certain category of objects. But we do find by a בור that
it's exempt by a category of objects, כלים. So we're also going
to say this exemption of פסולי המוקדשים. Okay, and that allows us
to have these fun illustrations of a person, ox, and a well,
and when you can't collect from one, you collect from the other,
which goes like רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, everybody is 100%, and if
you can't divide it up, you go to those who you can
collect from.